[Music]
and this shorter version the 25-minute
fizz I'm going to be taking you through
what are called the seven modifiable
variables what that means are these are
the things you can change in your
workouts or how you program for the
workouts that will alter the adaptation
you get and then the end of the day
that's what we're all after right we're
trying to get a certain outcome is what
we call program design it's the specific
adaptation or desired a desired
adaptation and so we need to build a
cell can you know like you want a B and
C but not deep okay then I know exactly
how to modify this this and this to get
that adaptation that's all we're talking
about today so what are those seven
variables let's jump into it but before
we do that we've got to understand how
program design works first of all you
have to understand what you're training
for to begin with now I've got a
separate video on needs analysis I think
it's twenty-five or fifty five minutes I
can't remember but you need to run some
sort of testing as the point you can go
watch that video from there you
determine your goals and now we get to
our green step which is what the focus
of today is modifiable variables this
acronym Co for work that I like says hey
you need to do your goal is a will now
modify these seven things in this exact
fashion and you will then get a as an
adaptation hopefully that results in the
change in performance that you're
looking for and then from there you
would come back and redo the needs
analysis or at least a portion of it to
see what new goals you need to come up
with so that's the cycle if you will a
program design that we should be going
through for the most of the time we're
training an individual athlete or not
should be the same thing we always
should be training with the purpose we
should be doing that the best serve our
little bit of our abilities sorry so
let's jump right into it with the seven
modifiable variables
okay now the ones in the on the your
right or so I think ones in green
they're separated because those ones
influence each other directly so in
other words if you say reduce the rest
you take between reps that's probably
going to reduce the amount of volume
and/or intensity you can do if you go up
in intensity that's going to reduce
volume etc the other ones that are in
the pinkish grayish something color
whatever the hell that is they are
important of course but they're not
going to miss
barely guarantee direct relationship
with that with the other three and so
let's jump into those other ones first
starting with choice and we'll go
through order frequency progression
intensity volume in routes now I'm not
gonna give you the full monty on any one
of these variables cuz I've already
talked about them a lot and some of the
other videos so hey you can't get it all
for free gotta go well actually all of
it is free every single video I've ever
done is free there's nothing behind any
paywall ever so the hell with yourself
it is free but it's not free timewise
you're gonna have to spend some time
watching more the videos to pick up on
all the other stuff if not every video
would be like seven and a half hours and
my students would be very upset because
they watch the same thing multiple times
that's not good for anybody
anyways choice is this alright you want
to get a certain adaptation new client
comes you do needs analysis and you
determine or our training goal is a well
then you have to decide okay which
exercises do I select that's gonna put
me in the best position to get a now we
know from previous videos that exercises
themselves do not guarantee a certain
adaptation so you can't come and say
things like alright I want to get
stronger therefore I will pick a
deadlift exercise because that deadlift
is the best for strength that's not true
at all as I am close to true something
against deadlifts it's against your
brain right exercises themself do not
determine the adaptation it's how you do
them that matters
what's your rep ranges rests in
intensity things like that so if we look
at these two pictures I mean you're
trying to determine determine which of
these overhead squat exercises is going
quote better we can't do that because
exercises don't determine adaptation
what does determine the adaptation it's
the application assets the reps
intensity speed technique etc now the
exercises do determine certain things
like the movement playing you're in the
muscles you're using the types of
contractions and the technical
proficiency and so you may recognize
this slide from one of my other videos
I'm definitely not gonna go through it I
think I spent about 20 minutes on this
slide specifically but these are some
other things you would consider when
selecting the exercise right now old the
individuals their experience or mobility
their flexibility so in some cases you
may look at the traditional red squat
and say okay because of these five
reasons today this is a better exercise
selection than the one legged standing
on the medicine ball one-armed overhead
kettlebell squat other situations oh
maybe that's the better choice than a
traditional overhead squat but the point
I'm making is the exercises you selected
in your program do influence the
adaptation or they outcome a little bit
the next one
Co Co for vert is ordered now I'm
talking about order within a day so this
is you're gonna be doing four or five or
six different exercises a day which one
do you do first second third fourth now
look at the pictures below imagine
you're gonna go on the field and do some
agility work you're gonna do some
snatches for the day some deadlifts and
then you're gonna push a sled till you
throw up which ones do you do first
second and third well but basics of
exercise order would say this now it's
funny because if you're in my class 3:51
you're gonna be noticing there's a
structure to our entire class what do we
do first in the semester and what do we
do second third fourth fifth it's this
right so you technically do the fastest
things first so you do speed then power
then strength then I per trophy and any
conditioning or endurance work at the
end that's how I structure the class
right
surprise surprise so that's that's a
traditional exercise order now the
reason you do it this way is a couple of
things of course there's exceptions to
the rules but this is a general answer
okay number one if you do if you screw
up this order or you do it in the
inverse say you do your conditioning
first what you're gonna slow down your
speed you're not gonna be as strong
you'll be tired so they'll be able to
produce as much force and we know from
other videos if we sabotage our force
production our speed or our power output
we don't actually then get powerful or
strong alright so you may think it's
like a mental toughness thing or
something like that but you're using bad
physiology you're using that program
design and some people say things like
wow my athletes need to be able to
produce force or use their strength in
the fourth quarter fine if you want to
talk about maintaining your power over
time cool but that's different than
increasing your max power or your max
strength these are different things if
the goal is to increase your maximum
ability if you do conditioning first
you'll be too tired and you'll decrease
the benefit or the productivity for your
speed power strength sup doing speed
work first doesn't have that effect on
conditioning no one will ever have a
less of a pump on their workout because
they need power stuff before they went
and did their hyper tree session and so
we have a cost-benefit thing to run here
if I do the conditioning endurance stuff
first it's gonna compromise my speed
power strength if I do my speed power
strength stuff first it doesn't
compromise my conditioning or my
hypertrophy at all so there's a hundred
percent win no loss scenario and doing
it in this order the other thing to
consider is the possibility of injury so
imagine you just did a thousand push-ups
and burpees and overhead presses for
time and now well my shoulder joint is
incredibly fatigued my stabilizer
muscles which are not big and strong
muscles are fatigued and now I'm gonna
actually put them a scenario where when
I ask them to move fast and at a maximum
load you're gonna increase likelihood
that giving out so for those two primary
reasons again number one you're gonna
compromise your strength and by strength
I mean speed power strength anything
like that and number two our chances of
injury probably go up a little bit so we
want to make sure we do our conditioning
and hypertrophy or whatever that is at
the end okay so that's exercise order
within a day F in our scenario here is
called frequency and don't memorize this
chart at all it's just showing the
concept of frequency refers to how many
days a week you're training so somebody
of course in like the offseason it's
gonna be training for six times a week
and again training we're typically
referring to in the weight room stuff
cannot support training but of course in
competition in the middle of a season
you're not gonna be left in five days a
week once twice a week is probably
pretty good because you have so much
stuff going on in competition you come
out of that post season you ramp it up a
little bit you get the ID here so points
just being frequency refers to how many
days a week are you training if you're a
competitive athletes say Olympic
weightlifter or a power lifter you might
even be training
got an MMA that's not uncommon for the
ounces I work with to train 14 to 18
times a week do the quick math there but
that means they're training two to three
times a day pretty consistently alright
so let's move on those last three now
volume intensity and rest volume
mathematically is repetitions times sets
so if you did three sets of ten
repetitions your volume for the day
would be thirty now we usually report
this as a weekly total you can do
whatever you want but in my class for
example on your mesocycle project you're
going to count up the total amount of
repetitions you did in every one of your
eight weeks and then you're gonna plot
that so week one total repetitions with
two hundred week twos repetitions 300
week three etc etc now don't go from 200
300 right other videos we've talked
about this but you generally don't want
to increase volume by more than ten
percent or so a weak point being though
you can up the total amount of
repetitions that you do by that simple
math that I just explained to you come
back and look at this again when you do
your mesocycle project if you get
confused but nonetheless now there's
another term that I like called volume
load and this is the same thing as
volume abut you multiply it by the load
load is a way of saying well how much
did you lift a lot of practitioners are
gonna tell you they actually like this a
lot better because volume doesn't really
explain what's going on the body think
of it this way imagine athlete a did
three sets of ten repetitions at fifty
pounds okay so that's 30 repetitions at
50 pounds that's 1500 total pounds I
moved another athlete did three sets of
10 repetitions at 500 pounds if I only
looked at volume both would just be at
30 but if I look at volume multiplied by
how much they actually lifted we've got
1500 multiplied by a whole lot more than
so volume load is probably a little bit
more telling and a better indicator of
what's actually stressing on the body
and how much fatigue they're
experiencing which is the only reason
for calculating volume we're trying to
manage fatigue over time intensity is
what we call the percentage of your one
rep max so intensity
in the case of science and physiology is
not a subjective trim saw that was
really intense workout no was it or was
it not
what percentage everyone at max was it
that determines intensity so when we're
speaking like that that's what we're
referring to how heavy was it and how
many reps how many sets to totally do
when we report in Tennessee though again
for the mesocycle you'll do this it's
typically as a average weekly so don't
go count up all the intensities because
they're all percentages and report a
weekly intensity of 938 it's not gonna
make any sense what you're gonna do is
kind of take all the repetitions say you
know what like for the most part most of
Monday was at 75% most of Tuesday was at
80% most of Wednesday was at 90% so
alright the average weekly volume was
82% or whatever that was going to be
right now volume and intensity in
intensity are inversely related if you
do three repetitions you can only do so
much weight say 90% now if I go to do
five repetitions I have to drop the
weight there's just no way or wouldn't
be a same number I can't do two
repetitions at my one at max by
definition then that wouldn't be my one
rep max
so opposite if I add load I can't do as
many repetitions if I'm really at that
percent right so we have to appreciate
understand what happens with volume
intensity since we're getting to the end
of the semester in class now hopefully
you can build out a schematic like this
I think this is a fantastic way to study
for your final exam and those of you at
home and they should go look at the same
thing as well what I've plotted here is
that relative percentage or intensity
and I've kind of laid out all the
different training adaptations we
discuss in my class and where they would
land I'm not going to go through all of
them now cuz I've done this in all of
their own individual videos you could do
this same thing with repetitions per set
though pay attention to a couple of
things on both of these slides though
notice how some of them go below 0 and
above 400% how is this possible think
through that Cole watch the other videos
same thing with repetitions and it can't
be less than 0 reps but some of these go
really high into the repetition ranges
right so you should be able to without
looking at a cheat sheet here be able to
know
what intensity and what rep range do I
do for all the different adaptations
that we've covered this year we've been
working on a scorecard as well so here's
all of them in that same thing and I've
also added things like choice and order
to it so you can see for example when
you're going to choose the exercises for
speed just choose an exercise that
allows you to move fast good example a
deadlift a deadlift is not a great
choice for speed because it's really
hard to do it fast without smack on your
knee so choose a better exercise
probably same thing a bicep curl were
probably not doing bicep curls for speed
but we could do pull-ups for speed we
could do bent row for speed of course we
could do any running or moving and
things like that either into the
spectrum take a look at muscular
endurance
we might select our exercises by either
the muscle we're specifically wanting to
work or the movement pattern that would
be even one of those would be acceptable
meses methods for choosing the exercise
but if we counter that with something
like strength we don't really choose
often our for training for strength the
exercise we want by a certain muscle
group we're usually training movement
patterns there alright so again
depending on the adaptation you're
looking for how you select your
exercises or the exercise choice
variable changes depending on the
adaptation you can see the basic
exercise order that we've covered all
year and that's in there as well the
repetition range present intensities and
of course the rest intervals at the very
bottom so we'll work on this in class
don't worry our last modifiable bit
variable the P and Copa verb is
progression so we referring to here now
is how do we progress the program over
time now we'll have more slides we'll
talk more specifically about
periodization but really this is the
concept and you've also seen this slide
before the concepts are few the methods
are many you've also heard people say
things like well coaching as a science
and an art well really what they're
saying is the science e part are the
concepts the art part are the methods ok
so as long as you're hitting these
concepts your program will probably work
in terms of make sure you're selecting
the adaptation
that you want to go for based on these
analysis make sure that you are
progressively overloading somehow that
doesn't always necessarily mean my
intensity could be by volume so you
overload the distance you are covering
or overload the amount of work you do
could be by speed it could be by
reducing nest intervals a whole bunch of
ways we can progress over time but it
has to be some sort of progressive
overload and while doing that we want to
balance stress and recovery which is
really all peer Dacian is we want to
what I call balanced said and healthy D
so said being specific out of page
adaptation to imposed a man which is
specificity right so if you want to get
better at push-ups you can't just do
push-ups every day you're gonna blow
your shoulders up so I also can't just
do a bunch of upper back rehab and think
I'm gonna get better at bench pressing
so I want to do some specificity but I
also want to do some long-term athletic
development stuff and we want to balance
that right okay so a little bit of very
specific work but then a little bit of
maintenance work a little bit of
foundation work some sort of balance
about how much you do if each is really
complicated answer but you got to have
some of both in the category and then do
whatever you got to do to maximize
adherence people got to do the program
from the art stuff hey that's up for you
to decide
do you like to train the morning so
you'd like to train at night you like
those speakers going and a whole crowd
of people there to train by yourself in
your garage that's really all look to
you unless important so that's it those
are the seven modifiable variables of
program design if you could do me a huge
huge favor go have a great day
that's it
[Music]